<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly inuectiue in the defence of the Gospell against such as murmure and woorke what thei can that the Bible shoulde not haue free passage, veray necessary to be red of euery faythfull Christian.</title>
            <author>Gerrard, Philip.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103091</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838848</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838848</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01657)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 45:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly inuectiue in the defence of the Gospell against such as murmure and woorke what thei can that the Bible shoulde not haue free passage, veray necessary to be red of euery faythfull Christian.</title>
                  <author>Gerrard, Philip.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the parishe of Christes Church within new gate by Richard Grafton, prynter to our soueraigne lorde Kyng Edward the. vi.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: Philippe Gerrard.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The inuectiue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:1"/>
            <p>A Godly Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue in the defence of the Goſpell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mure and woorke what thei can that the Bible ſhoulde not haue free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, veray neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary to be red of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery faythfull Chriſtian.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The abundaunte grace of the holie ghoſt maye dayly prouoke, tempt and ſtere vp the heart of oure mooſte noble and vertuous King <hi>EDVVARDE</hi> the <hi>.VI.</hi> king of England, Fraunce and Irelande. Defendour of the Faith, and in earth the ſupreme heade of the Churches of England and Ireland: earneſtly to promote the Goſpell of Chriſt, to the mayntenaunce of true religion and vertue.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN</hi> I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed often with my ſelfe that the leſt part of amitee faithfull loue and duety, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man oweth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde his natiue countrey. (My mooſte gracious and drad ſoueraigne lord) is not ſhewed in the gentle admonyſhyng his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey menne of ſuche faultes, perilles, and daungers, whiche either bee eminent or els playnly apparant: yea, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to attempte this thing when
<pb facs="tcp:3237:3"/> he ſeeth that there is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome great and plentifull occaſion. Euen now therfore I thought it good to ſet furth this Inuectiue in the defence of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des holy woord, againſt all cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians wilfully minded, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſtubburnely reſiſte the promoting of Chryſtes bleſſed Teſtament.</p>
            <p>I truſte wel therfore that your high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes eſpecially, and all your nobilitee, with other your true and faythefull ſubiectes, that haue earneſt heartes to promote Goddes glory, and to ſeeke for his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kyngdome, wil take in good part this my enterprice. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in although ther want fine handling, liuelye colours, the conueighance of Rhethoricke, and alſo quickneſſe of Witte: yet for al that, there hath wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted no iote of good will, for though I may moſt iuſtly confeſſe, I geue place vnto all men in good learnyng, yet I maye truely ſay, I am inferiour vnto fewe in good affection towardes the ſame. Therfore after this my rude and baſe ſtile of Inueiynge, I haue here ſet forth the minde and pleaſure of <hi>GOD,</hi> thynges veray commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and fruitefull for the weale of this noble realme, profitable to auoide
<pb facs="tcp:3237:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> contencion and to ſette amongeſt vs a louely ſocietie of liuyng. Nowe in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I entreate of cauſes ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary (moſt noble &amp; victoriouſe Kyng) I conceiue no ſmal hope, that no man if godly exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue place in his heart, will refuſe accordingly to note &amp; print the ſame moſt firmely in mind: eſpecially ſuch as the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh againſt, they haue eies and cannot ſee, they haue eares and heare not, for they ſhall well and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilye perceaue that ſtubburnneſſe of mind, hardnes of heart, the contempt of Goddes holy woord, the forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the great benefites and Godly goodneſſe of <hi>GOD,</hi> to bee thynges moſt greuouſly condempned in holye Scripture. Again thoſe that be alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ady bent and kendeled in affection to attayne the knowledge and due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience that apperteine to Chriſtes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyll and Teſtament, ſhal perceiue manifeſtly theim ſelfes to knowe the ſumme and effecte of their creacion. Wherof we ſhuld al be fully taught, and often admoniſhed alſo that we ar not borne to ſpend our time in paſtime and vanities of this miſerable world: but to be buſied in al ſeriouſe &amp; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3237:4"/> matters, chefely deſiryng to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Goddes holy religion, to liue innocently, yea and to excell in al kynd of vertues. For who ſo deſireth not to liue well (as Diogenes wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) liueth vainly. That is to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a vaine life, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men rather ſhew them ſelfes beaſtes mortal, then men Immortal, regardyng altogether the bodye that vile and beaſtely parte of man. But nowe (the pamperyng of it laied apart) yf we would conſidre the great and exuberant glory of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite or ſolle of man: if we wold weigh what ſtrength power and vertue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in the minde, wee woulde bee ſone perſwaded to folow Godly thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and flee the wicked. But more it is pitie, ſuche is the miſerable miſery of the world in theſe daies, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the ſaiyng of the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete: Woe is me, al is ful of ſinners, whiche offend of purpoſe and malice. Eſaie the .xxiiii. Theſe wilfull offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (my ſoueraigne Lorde) bee ſuche as maliciouſly ſpurne agaynſt the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely woorde of <hi>GOD,</hi> and enuy at your graces pore ſubiectes enbracing and readyng the ſame: vſynge ſubtyll and wicked perſwaſions to diſcorage
<pb facs="tcp:3237:4"/> men from the readyng therof, whiche thing forſoth both requireth correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſpedye confutacion for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhmente of the younge and tendre knowledge that <hi>GOD</hi> hath ſente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs. Vndoubtedly the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and cankered ſtomackes are ſo playne and plentiful in diuers places againſt the word of God, that no tong can be ſtill, ne yet heart permit with a diſſemblyng countenance to winke at the great ignorance &amp; ſubtile co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, eſpecially of ſuche as haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on theym to bee the lyghte of the worlde and guides ouer the ſimple to conducte theym to the true woorde of <hi>GOD.</hi> This thynge is ſoo euydent, that euery honeſte hearte woulde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to ſee it, and take peine to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, and wee oughte to bee earneſt in this. For who ſo regardeth the wyl of <hi>GOD,</hi> wyl openly defend the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of his Goſpel, and labour al that he can to winne mennes heartes to it. Yea, and to attempte this thyng, the vertue of Goddes word geueth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſtrengthe and boldenes.</p>
            <p>Euen nowe in conſideracion of this. I as one hyghly reioyſyng to ſee the glorie of <hi>GOD</hi> ſo liuely ſet furthe
<pb facs="tcp:3237:5"/> emongeſt vs, but ſorowyng agayne in my hearte to beholde the ſuperſticy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and ignoraunt ſorte ſo lyttell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, thoughte it full time to ſette forthe this Inuectiue, truſtynge that after the readyng of it, ſuche as haue wytte, reaſon and iudgemente, wyll remembre them ſelfes, aryſe and moſt reuerently mete the truth face to face, and be no longer diſceiued with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaited, coulered, and cloked thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but from hens forthe ioyeouſlye take in their handes the holy Bible, and eſteme it as the moſte diuine and Godly thyng that euer came amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs: yea and laboure with hande and foote vſyng ſobre &amp; catholicke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacions to allure me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it. This ſhoulde be a meane to ſette for euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs a publique quietnes, true loue, ſure and faithfull frendſhyppe. By this meane forſoth we ſhoulde ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe Ypocriſie and ignoraunce, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bee euer brawlyng and ſtande in contencion for euery colde Ceremonie and tryfelyng tradicion. For trewely where Ignoraunce, Diſdayne, the contempte of Goddes woorde gooe at their libertie, there muſt nedes aryſe contencion, brawlyng, ſedicion, and
<pb facs="tcp:3237:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> controuerſie in Opinions. Yea where an obediente and humble heart wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth toward the truthe, there for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lyght occaſion, thus men contend. Thou art an Hereticke ſaith one, thou arte a Papiſt ſaieth an other, by this forſoth the worde of <hi>GOD</hi> is ſore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domaged, by this meane Godlye and brotherlye exhortacion is put out of place, yea by this meane Sathan wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth his wyll and pleaſure and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth mennes heartes towarde the ſhining light to their owne condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion and vtter confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my deere ſoueraigne) who wold not lament? and for veray pitie tendre the poore ſimple people readye to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or rather thus periſhing for lacke of true erudicion, and broughte into ſuch amaſed dulnes through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie of preachers, that thei know not well whom to truſte. It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſary to ſet trouthe forward, and to exhorte all men to cleaue faſte vnto the worde of <hi>GOD,</hi> yea, and to admoniſhe theym not to contende for ſmall tryfles and lyghte occaſions: but to vſe ſobre and familier commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacion in matters of oure religion, for yf they pondre well howe GOD
<pb facs="tcp:3237:6"/> abhorreth contencion and diſcord, thei wyl bee ſore aſhamed to enter into it.</p>
            <p>And that it ſoo long contineweth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs, (moſt preſtant prince) ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny are much to bee reproued, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuche as be profound in eloquence, expert in tonges and great in ſcience, for they ſhine and ſhewe gloriouſe to the world and dooe nothyng, but bear lumpyſhe heartes toward the truthe.</p>
            <p>They might compas thinges to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde all contencion, and fynd meane to frame vs al to bee of one mynde in the woorde of God. And in thus doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng they ſhoulde appeaſe the Ire of GOD, and worke mooſt ſtrongely in the defence of this noble realme. For this cannot be denied, that weale pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique is made ſure and perpetuall, where the worde of GOD is thanck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receaued, and the Kyng faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obeyed of his louyng ſubiectes. This thing cannot come to paſſe (moſt redoubted Kyng) tyll there bee a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint againſt ſuch as vſe outragious wordes againſt the readers of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor till the heartes of your graces ſubiectes be made more agreable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth, no nor til the Cleargie be brought alſo in ſuch loue and acquain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:3237:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> with the holy Bible, that they wil ſhew them ſelfes as ready to ſow as they be nowe to reape, and forgeat to truſt ſo muche as thei do to the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of their proſperitie and worldly dignitie: reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bryng this that they ar not to be eſtemed as hed rulers of the worlde, but as miniſters apoynted to diſpoſe thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that thei ar char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall, not the offices of menne but of GOD. This office wherwith they are ſo ſtreightely charged is to feede the people with the woorde of God, wherfore (moſt gracious King) now to conclude. Although I am not ſo able as willyng to put men in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of their dueties in theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and to refourme their folyſh and wicked contencion, yet I truſt youre grace will ſo gently conſidre my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that this rude Inuectiue maye fynd fauoure in your graces ſyght to gooe forth, to the encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of al youre graces louyng ſubiectes vnto the woord of GOD. Vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt humbly with heart &amp; minde we ought to pray, both that your highnes maye ſpedely folowe vertuouſe kynge Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua, whiche mooſte gently exhorted his people, willyng them to be excea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
<pb facs="tcp:3237:7"/> diligente to take beede vnto all thynges that were written in the law of the LORD, makyng alſo heartie requeſt vnto them to cleaue faſte vnto the Lord their GOD, and alſo that all the nobles and commons of this your realme may anſwere your grace again, (as the people did Ioſua) God forbid but that wee ſhoulde ſerue the Lorde our GOD. The Lord will we ſerue and his voice wyl we obey, that is the holy Bible and Chriſtes bleſſed Teſtament. Yf God geue them grace thus to dooe, then this your graces no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble realme ſhal alwaies be moſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warded and defended, &amp; the Lord (accordyng to his promiſe) ſhall geue your highneſſe proſperous ſucceſſe in al youre affaires, whoſe mercifull hande may alwaies defend your noble eſtate.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties faithful and humble ſeruaunt Philippe Gerrard yeoman of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre vnto your grace.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite (moſt gentle reader) to admoniſhe the of two thynges: the one is, that in alledgyng S. Paule I folow the Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of Eraſmus that famus &amp; renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med clarke, for he foloweth the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the doctours &amp; declareth thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges at full, yet ſwarueth he not from the text. The other is, wher as I was once determined to haue inueighed very vehemently with diuerſe quicke ſentences and thonderyng places of holy ſcripture, I haue gone from my purpoſe in that behalfe as one ſome thyng abaſhed to write &amp; put to light thinges that I might iuſtly haue ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto: yea, and very loth that any man ſhould reporte, that either in this or that I haue diſmeaſured, my penne. Wherfore (good reader) I deſyre the to take in good part this lame &amp; baſe Inuectiue, I ſhould rather haue ſayd rude and ſimple exhortacion. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not framed accordyng to thyne expectacion, holde the content: My traueile in this, is only to wynne men. For I haue heard ſay, that ſharp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:3237:8"/> in writyng hath been ſo noiſome to ſome, that they haue ſtraight caſt al vnderfoote and looked no further, whiche neuer ſyns could byde anye handelyng ne yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fourme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes to any kynd of truth or thinges iuſtly ſpoken, whoſe ſtubburne and wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full intentes I truſt wyll be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied, that I ſhal not nede to ſet forthe the vehement Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue whiche I haue in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to come forthe, if I perceiue hereafter iuſt occaſion to bee giuen. Thus fare well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:9"/>
            <head>THE INVECTIVE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe faythfull hertes we owe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to GOD for his euident tokens of loue towarde vs mooſt vile and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinners S. Paule ſheweth in the .v. to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains. (Chriſte ſaieth he) willyngly for our ſakes ſuffered death and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth away our offences with his blud His benignite and gentlenes here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs was exceadyng great, if wee diligently note and po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre, that he the creatour of all thynges, would die for vs moſt ſinfull creatures: That he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, fauteles, and moſt pure, would ſuffre ſuche Paſſyon to remedye and healpe our wickednes: yea and brefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the God Immortall woulde ſuffre moſt cruell and greuouſe tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes for the loue of men mortal. O hard hearted that wyl not be thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for this great gentlenes and high benignitie, calling to memory the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Iuell &amp; treaſure of his death? For true Innocencie and perfecte ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion (ſaith ſainct Paule) bee giuen
<pb facs="tcp:3237:10"/> freely by it, the .v. to the Galathians.</p>
            <p>O faithful Chriſtians, was not this a preciouſe reward? for this moſt high and heauenly gifte our dutie is ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drely againe with hearte and mind to loue hym: by his Godly merites and loue toward vs, wee ſhould bee quick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prouoked, for through his death we bee all dedicated vnto hym and ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in his mooſt holy and preciouſe blud, let vs therfore obey vnto hym. This obedience forſoth is chefely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our handes in folowyng of his doctryne, for it is not enough (as witneſſeth S. Paule) to bee dipped in water, neither to profeſſe Chriſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte all our hole life aunſwere vnto his doctrine: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which not to ſwarue one iote wee haue profeſſed in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time and haue made there an earneſte promiſe to bee of this bande and holy religion, yea and alwayes to humble our ſelfes vnto his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly doctrine. Euen nowe therfore, for the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of theſe thynges, let vs offre a mete and worthy oblacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for this our Godly profeſſion, that is a liuyng ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice pure and holy, pleaſant and ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptable before God, a reaſonable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, whiche is the ſacrifice of the
<pb facs="tcp:3237:10"/> mynd: For God is a ſprite and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure is gotten by the gyftes of the ſprite the .xii. to the Roma. The Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt witneſſeth alſo that Chryſte is fully ſatiſfied with a faithfull heart, ſaiyng, geue me thine heart &amp; I aſke no more. Now truely no man geueth his heart vnto God, but he that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the pleaſure, po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe and vanities of this vile world and with a ſyncere mynde bent onely on heauenly wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſeeketh to knowe the ſcriptures of Chriſt: for Godly wiſedom (as ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth S. Paule) deliteth in Godly and ſimple mindes: and therfore none of the princes of this world haue atteig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it: Neyther Pilate, neither An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas nor Cayphas, nor the Phariſees ne yet the deuelles although thei wer learned in the knowledge of worldly thynges, pufte vp and proude becauſe they knewe the lawe, neither proude princes deſerued to know this, no nor yet the curiouſe and haute Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiers. The .ii Corinthi. This Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is the Goſpel of Chriſt, which bringeth quicke and ſpedy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, as thou maiſt read in the .x. to the Romains: by the ſtrength and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of it al thynges haue their beyng
<pb facs="tcp:3237:11"/> both in heauen and yearth. This hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſdome which is the very wil and teſtament of our ſauiour Chryſte, putteth power, efficacy, and vertue, in the holy ſacramentes. By this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome whiche is the miſticall, holy &amp; gloriouſe ſcriptures of Chriſte our ſolles liue and haue their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all noriſhmente. Yea, and in receuyng this heauenly wiſedome, which is the bleſſed word of God, wee receaue the bodie of Chriſt: here dooeth appere by theſe woordes an excedyng grace and vertue of the liuely woord of God. Therfore whoſoeuer wil conſider the effectes therof and way with himſelf the pith thy puinctes of our chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion, deſiryng to find fauour, grace, and mercie at the handes of God, he muſt obediently (al ſuperſticion, falſe and intermingled doctrine and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ignoraunce vtterly ſet a part) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace nowe Chriſtes Goſpell, whiche reconcileth all menne to God, as thou ſhalt finde in the fourth to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyans: this reconciliacion loue and fauour he that wold not gladly haue yf he might, is to bee thoughte bothe madde and miſerable, for it is a thing farre aboue the beneuolence of hyghe
<pb facs="tcp:3237:11"/> kynges and mightie princes, it is ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore moſt gredily to be deſired. Nowe truely this grace and fauour al poore men may well and eaſely atteigne at the handes of God, whiche with ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; obedient heartes reade his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Teſtament and ſeke forth his ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and all that be thus occupyed are openly pronounced to bee very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in Goddes ſight. Accordyng to this ſaiyng of the holy Prophete. Bleſſed are they that ſeeke forthe thy teſtimonies and require thy law with all their heartes. By this it dooeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere that it is requiſite for al chriſten men eyther poore or riche to ſtudy the holy Bible and diligentely to ſearche forthe the wyll and pleaſure of God. Thou canſt not denye but that thyng is pleaſaunt and acceptable in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſighte that cauſeth him to geue his ſonne benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for as muche as wee ſee daily that benediction is not giuen but vnto ſuche chyldren as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their fathers mind and pleaſure? And that it is very nedefull, that all men ſhoulde bee perfectly taughte in the holy Scriptures. Eſaie the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet plainly declareth. It is a people (ſaith he) without vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng and
<pb facs="tcp:3237:12"/> therfore he that created them ſhal not fauour them and he that made theym ſhall not bee mercifull vnto them, the xxvii of Eſaie. By theſe wordes it is eaſy to bee iudged. That who ſo euer is not diligente to reade the woorde of God, falleth into his indignacion and fearfull diſpleaſure and wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth on ignorauntly as one voide and deſtitute of al grace to whoſe peruerſe mynd God wyl ſhewe no mercie: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is the greateſt plage and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that can chance vnto men. Now to auoide this wicked eſtate, who would not bee circumſpecte and willyng to take in his hand the holy Teſtament? Vndoubtedly he that through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and ignoraunce is ſo ſeduced that he hath it in meane eſtimacion, and to reade it hym ſelf is neyther couragy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe ne yet of good wyll to haue it ſet forthe by other, is in a miſerable caſe, Yea, the miſery of ſuch a man no tong can ſufficiently expreſſe, and yet to ſee howe wickedly many nowadaies bee confederate togither in a Deuelyſhe conſpiracie againſt the promotyng of it, is a thyng ſoore to bee lamented. And all that bee of this peruerſe and ſtubburne iudgement, bee more abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb facs="tcp:3237:12"/> in goddes ſight then wer the wicked and groſſe people of Gereſa, whiche coulde not away with Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes doctrine, regarded not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng vnto them, no nor woulde in no wiſe bee acquainted with hym, whoſe familiaritie and acquaintaunce eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chriſten man oughte deſirouſely to ſeeke. And this is plaine that there is none ſo good a meane to be throughly acquainted with him as to bee buſied in his holy ſcriptures, and alwaies to haue a delyghte there, folowyng the holy Prophete, whiche ſaid vnto god, thy commaundementes Lorde, bee my ioye and delectacion. This holy man beatyng alwaies a faithful heart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and euer diligent to ſet abrode the lawes of his Lord, ſaied vnto his deere and beſt beloued ſonne Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vnto all the people. Kepe &amp; ſeeke for the commaundementes of the lord your god that you may enioye a good land and inherite your chyldren after you for euer. This was Godly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill and worthie commendacion, this counſail ſhoulde all Chriſten men fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and gladly learn the ſyncere law of Chriſt, for it is ſpiritual and the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of life as thou arte taughte in the
<pb facs="tcp:3237:13"/> eight to the Romains. And in this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng wee muſt needes proſpre and goe forwarde in all our affayres. As it is ſhewed in the .xv. Chapyter .ii. of the Chronycles. Beleue his Prophetes and ſoo ſhall ye proſpere: Howe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully I praye you dyd kyng Ioſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat proſpere becauſe he forſoke Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als waies and walked vpryghtely in Goddes commaundementes, obeyed the holy prophetes, and vtterly ſhoke of all the wycked dooeynges of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, euen for the earneſt heart he hadde vnto the truthe. God alwaies defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hym and ſtablyſhed his kyngdom in his handes, and ſo hathe he promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto all kynges &amp; prynces, whoſe heartes are couragiouſe in the wayes of the Lorde. This noble Prince was nothyng forgeatfull to call in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie his loyall dewtie and faythefull obedyence towardes GOD his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour and gouernoure. He was the trueſt hearted Kyng vnto GOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DES woord that euer was annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or had charge ouer Chryſtes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion, for he was inflamed with ſuche zeale and faythfull affection of hearte to ſet abroade the lyuely word of GOD. That he ſente forthe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe
<pb facs="tcp:3237:13"/> of his Lordes, Prieſtes and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uytes and cauſed theym to carry the booke of the Lawe with theym and commaunded theim to teache the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all the Cities of Iuda. Hys couragiouſe and Pryncely hearte, for this his dooeyng cannot haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lawde and commendacion. For this (a man may well ſaye) O mooſte noble Ioſaphat, mooſt woorthily by this acte thou haſte gotten perpetuall memorie and alſo the Heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where thou reygneſt nowe in wonderfull ioye and felicitie.</p>
            <p>O happie Lordes, that in thoſe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es obedyently wente on ſoo Godlye a meſſage, and lyke trewe Subiectes ſhewed your ſelfes earneſt and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearted to accomplyſhe the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges commaundement, whiche emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt all actes of high kinges and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is moſt woorthily celebrated and had in renoume, as thou mayeſt reade in the notable hiſtory of Ioſaphat, ſet forth in the Bible: yea this act was ſo wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful vnto men &amp; ſo pleſant in the eyes of God, that by the reaſon therof al kynges &amp; princes feared vertuouſe Ioſaphat. For he wrought moſt nobly folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his guide &amp; capitain the holy
<pb facs="tcp:3237:14"/> ghoſt whiche maketh all men feruent in the feare of the Lord, Eſaye the .xi. Yea, alwaies be conſidered the great kyndnes, giftes and benefites of God He knewe ryght well that who ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteth in the lawe of the Lorde, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth him ſelf therein both day and nyght muſt needes proſpere and dooe thynges acceptable before God. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore he being euer te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre ouer the weale of his ſubiects, and pretendyng moſt nobly to defend equitie and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice appoineted iudges in euery Citie and ſtraightely bade them: Feare the Lord, dooe Iuſtice, regard not one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more then another, take ye no rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of them, bee couragiouſe, for the Lord wyll bee with the good. Herken to noble Ioſephat all chriſten princes whom God hath appoincted to guide and conduct his people in his holy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies and Godly preceptes: And alſo other inferiour powers may take exaumple and learne of hym as of the comlieſt and nobleſt Prince that euer bare renoume. His vertuouſe actes would God they woulde humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, and ſette before their faces his wonderful Godly dooynges, yea and learne nowe to promote the Goſpel of
<pb facs="tcp:3237:14"/> Chriſt &amp; to ſtere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this ſo godly a worke the ſaiyng of Eſay is a ſtronge perſwaſion &amp; a great encouragement to read the goſpell, aſſone as thy iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes are knowen vnto the world then the inhabiters of the earth learn rightwiſenes. Eſay the .xxvi. whiche vndoubtedly is a thyng as neceſſary to be learned at this daye as any one thyng vnder heauen. Yf men woulde weygh the handelyng of thynges and howe pitiefully the poore be oppreſſed of the ryche, and for amendemente of this thyng: Let vs all praye with the holy Prophete Eſay (Oh Lord) nowe healpe, for thou art the poore mannes healpe, a ſtrenghte for the nedefull in his neceſſitie. Eſay the .xxv. and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs all to miniſter vnto the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye wee reade a Godly ſaiyng in the Prophet Dauid, whereon reſteth the ſumme and effect of our chriſtianitie. That is, bleſſed is he that hathe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte vnto the poore, and conſidereth his neceſſitie, in the yl day the Lorde wyll freely deliuer him. Here forſoth is a wonderfull Godly promiſe vnto ſuche as bee pitiefull and tendre ouer the poore. And who ſo wyll not with heart and mynd geue vnto them thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:3237:15"/> neceſſarye, but tourneth his face from them and hautely ouer looketh them, not willyng to offre vnto thoſe liuely Images of God, meate, drinke, raiment with other nedefull thynges he ſhall then bee appoincted into euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtyng puniſhemente of Hell, a place for the mercileſſe ordeyned of God.</p>
            <p>Verily this ſhalbee full iudgemente and perfecte ſentence ſpoken of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des owne mouthe in that terrible day awaye ye wicked and mercileſſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into euerlaſtyng fire. Then ſhal honour, pompe and dignitie nothyng auayle, then ſhall theſe great poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of goodes pitiefully crye alas, and bewail their infelicitie and great lacke of grace: But now this to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre theyr heartes bee ouer hard. Who doeth not ſee how pitiefully the poore be deſpiſed in euery place, be not moſt men more ready to deuour them, then to healpe them, be they not haſtyer to make them ſtarke beggers, then to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cour &amp; to relefe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their neceſſitie? truely ouer al that thus do there han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the vengeance of god, wonderful Plages and myſeries, euen ſuche as hanged ouer the wycked Diues ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the Goſpell, and lette all of
<pb facs="tcp:3237:15"/> his confederate feloweſhyppe (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of forſothe the nomber is greate) bee fully perſwaded in this, that it is not poſſyble that theſe impoueryſhers of the poore ſhoulde alwayes proſpere, but that eyther they or theyr heyres ſhoulde falle in ſome myſerye and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne decaye and mooſt commonly to ſpreade abrode their euel gotten goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des as thou maieſt plainly read in the xij. of Iob. Aand how to vſe the poore all chryſten men maye nowe learne of that vertuouſe man whoſe charitable ſaiyng ſhould neuer out of our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that is, I deliuered the pore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cryed and the fatherles that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted healp, the .xxix. of Iob. Iob conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred full well that God was none of them that vſed parcialitie, no nor yet any acceptour of perſonnes and that made hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo plainly to affirme that god regardeth not the riche man more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore, Iob .xxxiiii. but verily the cauſe that many paſſe ſo litel to tread the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnderfote &amp; with wicked oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vtterly to vndoe thei care not how many, is a certein greedy deſire to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulate riches, to mainteine world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pompe and dignitie, and to haue the blynde prayſes and vayne commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacions
<pb facs="tcp:3237:16"/> of this deceiptefull worlde, as to be eſtemed very riche, and as the common ſaiyng is, he is one yf he liue that will proue a great riche man, by his witte and policie he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thus muche. Where this ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie reigneth, vertue and Godlyneſſe muſt nedes be put a ſyde. And by none other mean moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly theſe great ryches and vaine tytles bee attaigned but by vſurye, gyftes, brybes, and in diſceauing the poore. O thou moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and infortunate man that by this meane waxeſt riche? Heare what a wonderfull plage hangeth ouer thy heade. The fyre ſhal conſume ſuche as bee greedy to receiue gyftes, for they beare miſchefe in their bodies &amp; bring forth deceipte. The .xviii of Iob. Oh Lord, dooeth not I pray you eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now the ſtate of this woorlde declare, (yf you marke well) that the ſore threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenynges of God, the reward of ſinne as death, Hell and eternall dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to bee thinges nether thought v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne yet feared in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes conſcience? For yf they feared God and had the ſtrength of his ſpirite, all the ryches &amp; glory of this world could not moue them to thinke the contrary, but that
<pb facs="tcp:3237:16"/> it were much better for them to helpe the poore, and to be confourmable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Goddes commaundement, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelyſhely to treade theim vnder foote for wicked Mammon and filthy lucar ſake. Suffre not your eies thus to bee blinded with vanities, it is ſeen daily that miſers and vile abiectes, euen ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as bee brutyſhe both in mynd and body for their ryches ſake to be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtemed and pufte vp in pride. The rude and gaſyng multitude iudge all ſuche men to be in highe ioye and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, for their vncertain and tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rycheſſe, thynke thou them neuer a deele the better. But ſorowe and bee carefull in thyne heart, that Auarice and inſaciate couetouſnes reigne ſoo ſoore amongeſt them, that to dooe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe they haue cleane forgotten, for the common reliefe that they beſtowe vpon the needy bee fayre woordes, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lored with Hypocriſye, as, alas good man, God healpe the, god healpe the. O counterfaited Chriſtian, god com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the to healpe them: and cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed arte thou of what degree ſoo euer thou arte, that wylt not ſuccoure thy poore neyghbour in his neceſſitie. Bee penitent therfore in time, for dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
<pb facs="tcp:3237:17"/> hangeth ouer thy hed. I ſuppoſe thou ſeeſt plainely inough what miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and myſchefe reigne euery where The poore bee deſpyſed and Goddes woord ſo lytell regarded and thought vpon, that that ſoore and lamentable ſaiyng of Eſaye maie iuſtely bee ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto vs in theſe daies. It is an ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinate people, vnfaithefull chyldren, (ſaieth he) chyldren that wil not here the law of the Lord, the .xxix. of Eſai.</p>
            <p>O noble Englande this lawe of the Lord thou haſt moſte plainly ſet forth vnto the &amp; as yet thy myſerable ſtate is ſoore to bee lamented, for through thy obſtinate blindnes thou prouokeſt God to ſtryke ſtyll with durable ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, thou dooeſt not ſoo humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte thy ſelf vnto his bleſſed wil and teſtament as thy duetie is. Thou arte neyther ſoo ioyouſe, ne yet ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent to haue it goe forward as God hath geuen the occaſions within theſe fewe yeres. It ſemeth thine hearte is ſetled on fantaſies moſt fond, and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt olde dotyng dreames foo faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der locke, yea, and ſauereſt ſo much of auncient cuſtome that the pure worde of God in thy ſpirite hath ſmal taſte. But heare a whyle and geue eare and
<pb facs="tcp:3237:17"/> thou ſhalte knowe more of thy duetie, and determine thy ſelfe lowely to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſuche hiſtories as ſhall be reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto the gathered out of the lawe of the Lord. Firſt conſidre when that holye man Eſdras Preached vnto the people their eares were ſo wonderful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly enclyned to the booke of the lawe, and their heartes ſo enamored for the ſinguler delight they had to heare the ſwete wordes and pleaſant promiſes of god, that they could not but weepe the .ii. booke of Eſdras the .viii. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Forſothe it was a greate token of grace to weepe for the feruente zeale and loue of Goddes worde. Thei alſo made greate myrthe becauſe they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode what was declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>O happie people that ſo reioyſed in knowledge. What man is he diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng downe into hymſelfe that wold not reioyſe alſo to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what ioye and felycitie theſe people had in the woord of God: and mourne nowe for compaſſion to beholde what ſpite and euell wyl many beare toward the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bible? whoſe miſerable blyndneſſe is muche to be lamented, truely ſuche is the peſtilent malice of ignorantes, ſuche bee the deceiptes and wyles of
<pb facs="tcp:3237:18"/> Ipocrites, the one in league and full conſente with the other, labour with all ſubtilitie to wrappe the people in blyndneſſe ſtyl, and yet openlye they faigne theym ſelfes glad and ioyouſe that the truthe is come out, but ſorow and ſigh in their heartes to haue it go forwarde. Great pytie it is that any manne ſhould goe about to endomage Chriſten men in the word of God: For the greateſt compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we ought to haue on any one thyng vnder Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is on the rude multitude of Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians lackyng the trewe knowledge therof: for Chryſten mennes heartes ſhoulde alwaies bee encloſed in that highe and heauenly wiſedom of God, conſideryng that Ignoraunce is the moſt peſtilent poyſon that can reigne emongeſt men. And to learne howe to abbolyſhe the great and wonderfull blyndnes, whiche hathe hadde a long courſe and continuance emongeſt vs, thou haſte the holy Byble playnely ſet forth vnto the: and yf thou haue a hoole and a cleare heart, thou mayeſt ſone learne to folowe the trace of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, thou ſhalte learne alſo to be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and quiete to beare al afflictions, yea, and ſhalte be able to enſtruct ſuche as
<pb facs="tcp:3237:18"/> thou haſte nouryſhed to liue togither in an amiable conuerſacion. But alas there be many both temporal and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall that wyll neuer take the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their handes, they paſſe lyght of it, &amp; care not howe lyttell it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of emongeſt them, but &amp; if it come by chance vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they eſteme it as a geaſt nether welcome ne yet loked for. Of what ſpirite they learne this of, I muche marueil, yf one call them coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfaited chriſtians ryght ſcribes and Phariſeis, they ſet vp their bryſtels and fall in a rage. Oh Lord ſuche are nothyng mindfull of the ſaiyng of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephas vnto Iob, receaue the lawe at the Lordes mouthe and laie vppe his woordes in thyne hearte and he ſhall geue the an harueſt with ſuche plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull abundaunce that it ſhal exceade the duſte of the yearthe, and looke what thou takeſt in hand it ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpere. Nowe Englande this Godly ſaiyng ſhoulde ſteere vp the and all thyne to ſhewe your ſelfes moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and meke in ſettyng forwarde the woorde of GOD: Surely thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueſte greate glorye and hyghe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtymacion, yf thou bee agreable vnto his truthe. And therfore ſhewe thy
<pb facs="tcp:3237:19"/> ſelfe euer couragiouſe to promote his bleſſed teſtament, and ceaſe now to be ſtyffenecked to deſende thy ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and wilfull ignoraunce, for this is playne, no man ſhal bee excuſed by ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ne yet ſhal eſcape to geue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte of his bailywicke. Thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt therefore obedientlye enbrace the liuely woord of God, which is a thing moſt mete and requiſite for all agees and degrees of men. Thou ſhouldeſt ſtudie the ſame both daye and nyghte, and geue thy ſelf wholy to knowe the Euangelion of Chryſte, for the eyes of the Lord behold all the earth to ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghthen them that are holie with him, the .xvi. Cha. the .ii. Chronicles. This kynde of ſtudie is moſt conuenable for the profeſſours of Chriſt, and thus to dooe is the chefeſt puincte of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in Baptime, whereunto yf you anſwere (as ſaieth ſainct Paule.) He that is moſt abiecte emongeſt you, is better then they that bee taken to bee of higheſt authoritie emongeſt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, the .i. to the Corinthians. Let vs nowe therfore plante ſurely in our hertes the lawe of God. Let vs ſhewe our ſelfes ioyouſe to heare the eternal teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt ſpoken of emongeſt
<pb facs="tcp:3237:19"/> vs, Let vs remember well the ſaiyng of Samuell vnto Saull. Thou haſte caſte awaye the biddyng of God, and therfore the Lord hath caſte the away alſo, This ſhoulde be no leſſe fearfull vnto vs nowe, leaſt the Lord caſt vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which maie and wyll not drinke of the well of the water of life, freely, that is the holy Bible moſt godly and ſyncerely ſet forthe in oure Engliſhe tongue. For the whiche wee oughte with reioyſyng heartes to ſaie. O the lot of our felicite moſt luckely chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. For where as of late we offred ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice vnto Idols, now we be taught to offre the ſacrifice of Iuſtice vnto our heauenly father. Of late we were obedyent vnto al damnable rites and wicked ſuperſticion, nowe we be tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to obey onely the Goſpell which is ſaluacion vnto al them that beleue it. It is not long ſythen we called on Sainctes for diſeaſes and all folyſhe fantaſies, nowe we be taught, that in all our extreme miſeries we ſhuld flee vnto Iheſus the only appoincted me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour betwyxt God the father and vs: Once we wer not aſhamed to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne barefooted and barelegged, &amp; to bowe our ſelfes vnto Images, before whom
<pb facs="tcp:3237:20"/> we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted wonderful Idolatrye, a thyng moſt curſed &amp; dampnable in the ſight of god. And if men woulde iuſtly weie &amp; pondre, the maruelouſe Ipocri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſy, Idolatrie &amp; dampnable ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which of late dayes were ſtifly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and mainteined of the Clergy, for pompe and dignitie, vayne glorye and aduauntage ſake, they cannot but tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe for this ſo Godly a change, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte they be priuie enemies vnto En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and ſhamefull rebels vnto chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes holy religion: for by this chaunge we haue lyght for darkenes, true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for ſuperſticion, remiſſion of our ſynnes by the bloud of Chriſt in ſtead of Papiſticall and deceitful Pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And yf we would call to memory howe imperfecte and corrupted oure faythe was by the reaſon of poperye, howe ignorantly we walked, yea, and what diſobedyence reygned emongeſt vs, then ſurely if we be not ſhameleſſe and deſtitute of all grace, wee cannot but giue hearty thankes for this moſt gloriouſe chaunce. And euen nowe is full tyme (yf the ſtate and value of thynges be wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered) to ſhew our ſelfes reuerent, deuout and ſymple to receiue the gloriouſe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:3237:20"/> yea, and to repente and make our eies ſore with ſobbing and wepyng that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we wer ſo diſceiued with popery, Ipocriſie &amp; ſuch other pelfe. And how to vſe our ſelfes in readyng the bible, let vs all take our exaumple of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe kyng Ioſias, whiche was a man indued with ſuch a ſinguler grace and of ſo ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t zeale toward the word of God, that after he had once redde the boke of the lord, he ſo lamented al wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doynges &amp; falſe doctrine that he rent his clothes and ſayd. The wrath of God is kendeled on vs, becauſe our fathers haue not hearkened vnto the wordes of this booke to do in al puin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes as it is written therein. O happy people of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, if your dull vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng wold reache to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how worthy wordes theſe wer for ſo noble a kyng, wold god the mindes of al kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges &amp; princes were ſo ſtable in the law of the Lorde as his was, for he ceaſed not with al his power to throw doun al kynd of idolatrie, as te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, hi laul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; groues. the .xxii. chro. &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly again, wicked Manaſſes &amp; his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſerued diſmael daies, made I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages &amp; bowed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: what vile e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy
<pb facs="tcp:3237:21"/> ſcrypture witneſſeth in the booke of the kynges. Where thou maieſt reade alſo of diuerſe kynges whoſe hyghe glory and worthineſſe is tourned into ſhame: for that thei refuſed the woord of God and gaue them ſelfes vnto I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie and vtterly caſt awaie the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God. And for an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample, How pitiefully I pray the did the lord ſmite kyng Iehoram? he was inuaded of his enemies and loſt al his goodes, he was plagued with diuerſe diſeaſes, his end was moſt miſerable &amp; greuouſe to beholde, for his bowelles rotted within hym and fell out of his bealy, yea, and to be brefe, for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe he was not buryed in the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of the kynges, but is left vnto vs as a memory of wickednes, the .xxii. Chronicles. This kyng was thus wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully plaged for that he forſoke the word of god, and defiled himſelf with Idolatrie againſt the law of the Lord And be ye wel aſſured, that he and his people wer not worſe defyled in thoſe dayes then wee were of late with Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſhe doctrine. Oure truſte was (as all men know) in maſſes of <hi>Scala celi.</hi> wee enbraced blynd pardones and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyngly buried them with vs: we kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb facs="tcp:3237:21"/> bowed and becked vnto Idolles: falſe doctrine bare the hole ſwaie, the truthe cleane ſhut vp, it was kept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der locke and coulde haue no libertie.</p>
            <p>What Godly minde woulde not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to thyncke on this? With theſe and many mo abhominacions we wer ſore and deadly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. And none ſo good a meane can now be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to cure oure olde diſeaſes, as to flee vnto the bleſſed teſtament of Chriſt, which wil quickely healpe ſuche as deſyre reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, confeſſynge their greefes and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentyng their myſerable blyndneſſe. The great grace and benignite of god is nowe ſoo preſte that thou maieſt yf thou wylte, drynke a draughte freelye of the ſyncere worde of God that moſt pure fountain and holſome water of lyfe, whiche wyll cauſe the to ſpewe vppe all that thou haſt dronke of that foule, ſtinkyng and Papiſtycal podel. And yf thou nowe geue no eare to it, but fondly wylte folowe other by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly bee thicke, thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berſome to iourney in, and haſt a deſire to ſtraie abrode thus wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thou knoweſt not whither, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainyng to folowe the doctrine of the Byble, where God ſheweth howe and
<pb facs="tcp:3237:22"/> whiche waye al his ſhould walke, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſoth it is an euident token and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificacion, that thou arte the childe of wrath a counterfaited Chriſtian, yea, and a ryght inheritour to Hell. And if thou be mynded to tary ſtill in Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and wilte not bee moued from thy miſerable condicion whyche ſoo blyndeth the that thou haſte no grace to diſcerne the contrariete of theſe .ii. doctrines, doe no more then but reade <hi>Sermones diſcipuli, Legenda Aurea, vitas Patrum,</hi> and the olde Chronicle of Romyſhe Byſhoppes, afterwarde reade the Teſtament. Then thou ſhalt ſoone eſpie how the glory of God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ben defaced, and what abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lyes and fables haue been taughte in the ſteade of the Goſpell. This ſhal bee a meane yf any meane be, to make thine hearte relente, this ſhall make the to crie out vpon all falſe doctrine: yea, this ſhall alter the from a ſtyffe and a ſtubburne ignorant to be a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt ſacrifice before GOD. That is thou ſhalte bee pourged in conſcyence from Idolatrie, Ipocriſie, ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, mennes conſtitucions, newe kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of worſhyppynges, this and that fourme of liuyng, colde ceremonies,
<pb facs="tcp:3237:22"/> and ſuch other pelfe as hath been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of late vnto Chryſtes doctryne, then thou wylte quickely refuſe the ſhadowes of the lawe of Moyſes and folowe the Teſtament, whiche is the lyghte and full perfection of Chriſtes holy religion, for there thou ſhalte fynde all thynges playnely ſet forthe vnto the, whiche apperteigne to get e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng lyfe. And if thou wilt now endeuour thy ſelf to attain the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, then forſoth thou traueleſt for pure orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, treaſures &amp; iuels and laborſt to a purpoſe, for in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of it al other ſtudies be but vain vanities and fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies moſt fond. And that thou mayeſt be more ſpedily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to the word of God, conſyder, howe ſore ſainct Paule as a true and faithfull miniſter was charged with thoughtes for the Congregacion.</p>
            <p>He was ſo earneſtly be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue it goe forewarde, that he coulde not ſuffre in no wyſe to haue it hyndered or put backe, but would haue it knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all kynd of menne as it ſhall apeare vnto the by theſe hys woordes vnto the Romaynes. I knowe wel (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) there bee many whyche bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:3237:23"/> the Goſpell of Chryſt, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sathanas goeth about to let the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men, the .xii. to the Romains. And yf ſainct Paul were nowe emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs, he would ſaie ſome thyng. It is to be thought he would breake out with a veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſprite and ſaie. O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters minyſters blynded with you knowe what, through you the woord of God cannot haue free paſſage, you ſtande gapyng for hygh and frail thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of the worlde, and bee nothyng myndefull that the Preachyng of the Goſpell farre ſurmounteth baptyme Maſſe and all other vertuouſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnder heauen. I ſaie vnto you, the preachyng of the Goſpell is the moſte pleaſant worſhippe and ſacrifice that can be vnto God, the firſt to the Rom. And for a farther trial of this, reuolue all the byble and thou ſhalt fynd this playn that the gloriouſt lyfe that can bee for a miniſter is to preach, and the ſhamfulleſt agen to be daintely noury<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; liue in idlenes, for of this (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all auncient writers) ariſe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchefes. Nowe therefore, who ſo hathe grace to remember his duety and hath alſo a cleare vnderſtandyng in the holy ſcriptures, wil ſay no leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3237:23"/> then ſainct Paule dyd. Woe be vnto me yf I preach not and ſet out the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of God. By this mean it ſhould be eaſie for all miniſters of the church to take away the great grefe and hatred out of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſtomakes. The cauſe truely why many report ſo euel of the Cleargie, is their manifeſt ſluggyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſtyffenes of mynde whereby they ſhewe them ſelfes ſalſe and faint hearted toward the woorde of God. This (I ſay) is the cauſe of their gret infamy, this is the cauſe that they are had nowe in ſuche diſdaine. It is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che maruail thei do not perceiue their owne perdicion. Wonderful it is that they can not ſmell why they are ſoo deſpyſed: Let them weigh the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter well and they cannot but confeſſe that it is no ſmall infamye for theym whiche ſhould be of great knowledge and experte in the Scryptures to bee founde as many are, who ſo lyſteth to put the thyng in profe and due exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion very Ideottes and of no know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, and the occaſion of this is, they are ſo choked with wilful ignorance, that they wyl not once loke on the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. They ſo perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, that thei ſaie al is wel inough and remayn
<pb facs="tcp:3237:24"/> ſtill euen hard hearted Pharoes tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde the ſhinyng lyghte, and as deefe as any doore nayle, yf a manne wyll them to ſtudie: pitie it is, that any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che miſerable miſerye ſhoulde reygne amongeſt them. But alas ſuche is the vayne vanitie of this worlde: They thynke ſtyll, that pompe and dignitie bryng eſtimacion, but the people haue nowe ſuche a ſyght that euery manne perceueth vertue to be a treaſure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy commendacion: and that for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues ſake euery minyſter is worthye double honour and not for his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And many perceiue right wel alſo that honor po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe and dignite were the bryngers in of the Biſhoppe of Rome and ſuche as Preache intermyngled doctryne for the mayntenaunce of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuche lyke dignitie and worldely eſtimacion, the people can ſoone eſpie, theyr flattery in Preachynge can not nowe bee cloked: There can no couert ſhadow theyr craftie conueiance eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially before ſuche as haue buſied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes in the doctrine of ſainct Paule whiche writeth thus. Thei that wold perſwade you contrarye thynges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that I haue taughte you fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe not GOD but mennes deſires
<pb facs="tcp:3237:24"/> and ſerue theyr owne vauntage, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and tirannye, and by all meanes poſſyble beware of ſuche. The fyfthe to the Galathians. Forſoth it woulde make men to wondre and to bee ſore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſed, yf they would ſearch forth old auncient hiſtories, to note what myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe menne haue wroughte for theyr owne aduauntage, and eſpecially to atteine fame and glory either by hoke or croke they paſſed not whether. Glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie as a thouſand hiſtories make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, hath euer been a ſtaie to keepe in the truthe. It is playne that it hathe called many a man from the ſtudye of the Byble, and whoſoeuer is geuen to maintein glory after his wicked will ſhall neuer agree with the Goſpell of Chryſte. Dyd not the Iewes I pray the to maynteygne theyr lawe, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was pompe, dignytie and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion, ſlaye the aucthour of lyfe and ryghtewyſenes? The eyghte Chapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Romayns. Yet forſoth they ſawe the lyghte, but malice blynded theyr eyes, they hearde the Goſpell but rancoure of hearte ſtopped theyr eares. The .x. chap. to the Romaines. They wer people of Goddes firſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but they refuſed his doctrine and
<pb facs="tcp:3237:25"/> for their incredulitie they were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reiecte and caſt of for naught. The cauſe was, they were ſo geuen to colde ceremonies, that they could not brooke the Goſpell. It was the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt peece of worke that euer Saincte Paule had to frame them vnto Chriſt, they ſtode euer ſo ſtyffe in the defence of their auncient cuſtomes, cloked and fained religion, yea, thei feared ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the fal of their gloriouſe kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e that as ye may reade they were ſoone confederate togither in myſchefe and agreed all on this quickely to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Chryſt and al his diſciples. They perceaued wel inough, that yf his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine had free courſe, thei might then take leaue of honour, pompe and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, wherein reſted all their preſente co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, ioye and felicitie. They knewe well alſo, that if the truthe were once knowen they could then no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude the poore ſymple people as they dyd, witneſſe Sainct Mathew. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nowe there be as ſtyffnecked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as euer were they. Attempte the thyng who luſteth, and he ſhall haue his handfull to bryng ſome rooted in ſuperſticiouſe doctryne to credite the Goſpell by the reaſon they giue ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:3237:25"/> confydence and are ſoo ſtayed with lewde perſuaſions of vnlearned prey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes which vnder the colour of ſheper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des plaie the righte wolfes: on whoſe ignoraunce the holye ſcripture cryeth out veray terribly in dyuerſe places, yea, it plainely pronounceth all ſuche to bee curſed and dampnable in the ſyghte of GOD, whiche haue taken on theym the offyce of myniſters and promotours of the goſpell, and nowe ſubtilie with their policies woulde keepe it in ſtaie. Would God all ſuch would graciouſly beare away the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of ſaincte Paule. I haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (ſaieth he) with all my power to ſatiſfie the office commaunded vnto me, the fourth to the Corint. If men had harkened vnto S. Paule in this poinct, chriſten kinges &amp; princes ſhuld neuer haue ben ſo corrupted &amp; defyled with Romiſh doctrine as thei wer, for the neglecting of preachyng, deſire of glorie, and ſubtil wreſting aſide of the ſcriptures in the beginning, cauſed i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to beare ſuch a ſtroke amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs, by litel &amp; litel the clergie wrought their feit, turning true thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to falſe vertue to lucar, pureſt and beſte to the worſte. Till the myndes of men were
<pb facs="tcp:3237:26"/> blinded altogither with wicked tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions. And nowe becauſe ſuche as ſhould preache, be ſtubburne to reſtore again true diſcipline, it ſtereth vp me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes heartes more &amp; more againſt them It is requiſite to pray for the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this and that they wold vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſafe to reade the Engliſhe Byble, yf the zeale of it once entre into theyr heartes, they wyll ſone forget al pey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and trauell taken in appliyng the ſame. Who is ignoraunte? he that ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieth the bible deſerueth great praiſe and is honorable before God. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarilye the prayer of hym that grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth at it is abhominable. theight cha of the Prouerbes. Woulde God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that you would read the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, for there you ſhall fynd euidently that the contemnours of the Bible be hated of God, abhominable before his eyes, chyldren of Sathanas and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritours vnto hel. This is a myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and terrible ſtate for any manne to thinke on. This wold make any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten conſcience to tremble and quake. This dilygently pondered who wold not lament with ſobbyng and weping eyes the great calamitie and myſerie of many a one amongeſt vs? it ſeemeth
<pb facs="tcp:3237:26"/> forſoth, that thei be cleane deſtitute of grace or els they would ſoone confeſſe that the fitteſt thyng that can bee for Chriſten men, were to knowe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſe teſtament of Chryſt, for in it bee conteigned woordes of life, ſentences ſpoken of Goddes owne mouthe, his aſſured and faithful promyſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we haue oure iuſte tytle to inherite his heauenly kingdome. Woe be vnto hym whoſoeuer he be that would not haue this ſo godly a thing knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and taught vnto all agees and degrees of men. Great pitie it is, but that al men baptyſed in the bleſſed blud of Chriſt, ſhould knowe his laſte wyll and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Teſtamente. And foraſmuche as chefe Learnyng and vertue is to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounte all other in good deedes, and this is in no place ſo fully taughte as in the Byble where thou ſhalte haue plentyfull inſtructions how to worke after Goddes wyll and pleaſure, and howe to fynd remedie againſt al euils and accuſtomed vices, what Engliſhe hert true vnto god &amp; faithful vnto the kyng wold murmure at it? It ſemeth that ſuche men be paſt ſhame or els de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryued of theyr wittes, that wyll not prouoke, tempte, and ſtere all men to
<pb facs="tcp:3237:27"/> ſtudie it. Maie not a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore with good reaſon, be bold to wryte againſte ſuche ſlouthefull ſheapardes as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnely ſtande nowe a daies and care not for knowledge? The frowarde ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce of ſuche is a greate blot and ſhame vnto other honeſte myniſters, whom forſothe wee oughte to haue in greate pryce, eſtimation and honoure and not in contempte or deryſion for the offences of the wycked, (as ſome haue theym nowe) for yf wee thus do we offend god greuouſly, and to loode the worſte of theim with checkes and tauntes is no waie forſothe to wynne them: chriſten charitie wyll rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that ſuche miniſters as haue noo knowledge in the Latin toungue, as fewe of them haue: would giue theim ſelfes ſome houre in the daie to reade the Englyſhe Byble, and wyll theym gentely not to be aſhamed to lerne. By this meane they maie recouer their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimacion againe. This woulde bee a quiet lyfe for them and a full reſtraint to ſtoppe mennes toungues. For ſoo longe as they whiche ſhoulde bee the lyghte of the worlde, will willyngly walke in darkeneſſe, diſdainyng the lyght, men wyll euer haue them in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:3237:27"/> and let them not thinke the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary but that they muſt nedes ſuffre infamy, diſdain and other great ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Fortune. Therfore frankely of their own courage if they haue grace, they will buſie them ſelfes in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Byble, as men nothyng forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of this, althoughe in times paſte thei lyued blyndly, ſwarued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and dyd ſeruice vnder Romiſh trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, yet maie they nowe in ſtudiyng it learne to be diſcrete miniſters. God graunt that they would encline vnto it with faithful, earneſt &amp; couragiouſe hertes. Surely it wer a token of great grace and a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable hearyng, that this rumor might be ſpred abrode eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where. In token that al the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ar penitent of falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; with one mynd wyl and voice all fully bent to ſet abrode the woorde of God euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his pulpyt exhorteth the flocke committed vnto his charge to reade the Englyſhe By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and make a greate ſhewe that they woulde haue it goe forwarde. Howe acceptable and pleaſaunt this wer in the eyes of God, the holy Prophetes bear witnes. And alſo howe commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyouſe it ſhoulde bee for the weale of
<pb facs="tcp:3237:28"/> this noble realme it nedeth no proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. For who wil denie his? the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt glorie for any realme is, when the prynce is couragiouſe to ſet forth the goſpell, and his ſubiectes obedient to receaue and promote the ſame. Our late kyng and deere ſoueraigne Lorde that was, as one verye graciouſe and tendre ouer the weale of his ſubiectes and again nothyng forgetefull of his dutie towarde God: For his parte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Bible to be had in euery churche. His grace ſente it out amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs in token and teſtimonial of his faithful and obedient heart vnto god. Yea, and in this doing he did but euen his bounden dutie and the office of a chryſten kyng. For ſainct Paule wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in the fyrſte to the Romaynes, that the lawe is not giuen onely to preiſtes, but indifferently vnto al kind of men. Maie not a man then with a ſorowfull hearte, greatly lamentyng the frowardneſſe and obſtinacie of the people, veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly crie out (as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Eſaye dyd) they haue made the eternall Teſtament of none effecte? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the .xxiiii. O wicked generacion which in thoſe daies regarded no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the will and pleaſure of their god.
<pb facs="tcp:3237:28"/> O ſhameleſſe wretches that ſo lightly caſt away their god. For their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto the truthe they haue lefte nowe in memorie a fayre iuell eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſhame. Compare vs and them togither and you ſhal fynd that we be their coſen germains and confederate frendes. Wee folowe a trade as wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as euer dyd they: We ſuffre the bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to lie in many Churches all duſtye here, vntouched there, raſe in this, and tourne in that. Not one curate amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt a great nomber exhorteth men vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to it. The ſheperdes forſothe eſteme it very lyghte: for whan they fynd men feedyng gredily on it becauſe it is of a ſwete leare and a ground moſt pleſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they chaſe them from it, it ſemeth ſuch ſheaperdes ſeeke the diſtruction of theyr ſhepe. Alas good men they ar ſo blynded with worldly wiſdome, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure and ſuperſticion that it is a dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the vnto them to ſee other men reade the ſcriptures. And yet they them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes wyll neuer take Byble nor Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in hand, but ſorowe &amp; ſigh with greuouſe gronynges, whan they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their great loſſe: for once they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued lyke Epicures and had al thinges at their willes, with their Images,
<pb facs="tcp:3237:29"/> pardones and Purgatory thei illuded many a ſeely pore ſolle. Thei duſked &amp; defaced the glorie of God &amp; made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfs rich. Thei ruled kinges &amp; nobles at their pleaſures and kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote, yea, thei were euer checke mate with the kyng, and ruled hym at their pleaſure, who ſo withſtode their deue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh doctrine did not long endure. The earneſt mainteners of Goddes woord felt alwaies their ſpitefull cruell and bluddy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. And to thinke wherfore many honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſuffred we ſhuld al reioyce, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidryng that loſſe of lyfe is an highe felicitie where perpetuall memory commeth in place. Thei that haue enterpriſed and emploied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes to do their dueties beſte towardes God, haue been ſoneſt ſnapt vppe, ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie hathe often ſoo ruled the roſte. Reade auncient hiſtories and you ſhal fynde this plaine. And nowe eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, great maruaill it is what vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes the minyſters find in the bible. Sins their dreames were taken from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they haue ſeldome ſaid where arte thou Lord? They folow lyghtnes and vanitie &amp; thinke it inoughe to ſtand at the aultre, although you ſtand at the alter, it doth not folow that you ar ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb facs="tcp:3237:29"/> to chriſt, for you are nere Chryſt &amp; ſtand worthelie at the aultre, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhew your ſelfes willyng to promote his holy Goſpel. Caſt of ſlouthe and ſharpe youre wyttes all blunte and dull with Ignoraunce. Haue ye not redde the woordes of the holye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete? I wyll delyghte (ſaieth he) in thy commaundementes as one that hathe founde great ſpoile and ryches, This holy Prophete reioyſed ſoo in his heart at the liuely woord of God, that he ſaied with a ſighe, Oh Lorde, howe ſweete bee thy woordes in the roffe of my mouthe: yea, they be ſwet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in my mouthe then the honicombe. He ſaied furthermore, the lawe of thy mouthe Lorde, is better to me then thouſandes of golde and ſyluer. Eſay the Prophete alſo as one ſome thyng offended with the miniſters, becauſe Goddes woord was not thankefully receaued, but eſtemed very lyghtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt them, for thei made falſehode theyr refuge and vanitie their guyde. Heare the woord of the LORD ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyre (ſayeth he) yee mockers whyche rule the people of Ieruſalem. Eſaye the, xxviii. Chapter. Theyr vayn con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce miſerable blindnes and wilful
<pb facs="tcp:3237:30"/> ententes engendred vexacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; brought continual vnquietenes vnto theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, yea, it ſo ſterred vp the ire and indignacion of God, that they wer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together troden vnderfote as myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abiectes. The lord deuyſed a mete handelyng, a worthy &amp; conuenient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainmente for ſuche ſheaperdes as wold not herken vnto his holy word. The Lord again hymſelfe perceauyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful wel the ſtubburnneſſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in reiecting his word, and alſo ſore offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ſee their ready willyng her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ſone enclyned vnto Idolatrie, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aketh thus. O ye people loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the woord of the Lord, Ieremie the fyrſte. Moreouer the Lord very deſirouſe to haue his ſtatutes promoted, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that his ſheperdes ſhuld ſe wel vnto and noryſhe their flocke, ſpeketh thus. O ye ſheperdes heare the worde of the Lord. Ezech. xxxiiii. in the ſame chapter he moſt pitiefully lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his ſeely pore ſhepe, he ſawe they were daily robbed and mooſte cruelly deuoured of all wylde rauenyng bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the felde, they runne blyndlye on what miſchefe thei luſt, for the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdes whiche ſhould haue been their guides and conducters, fed them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes
<pb facs="tcp:3237:30"/> onely with moſt daintie delycates and neuer regarded whiche waye the flocke went. The lord willing to haue his word that wel of grace and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler comfort moſt highly promoted, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he would cleane rydde and vtterly deliuer his people from Idolatrie: for the wycked Prophetes vſyng vnclean ſprites, falſe doctryne and deceiptful garmentes, ſhuld be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable deceiptours. And for the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die perfourmaunce of this, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded his ſwerd to aryſe, and plague as well the Ignoraunt people reiectyng his woord as the euell and ſuperſtyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe ſheperdes. Zacha. the .xiii. In a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother place alſo, the Lord mooſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſely offended with diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blyng my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, whiche wroughte altogether for lucar and gayne. I haue (ſaith he) no pleaſure in you, for whiche of you wyll kyndle fyre on myne Aultre for nought? The Lord affyrmed that they vnhalowed his Aultre, in that they ſayed it was not to be regarded, they onely thought not ſcorne &amp; made light of it, but they regarded muche leſſe what vile trumpery they offred vnto it, Malachie the fyrſt. The Englyſſhe Byble forſoth may well be compared
<pb facs="tcp:3237:31"/> vnto this aultre for ſuche as ſhoulde promote it and eſteme it moſt, laboure for gayne: they had rather worke a trentall of Maſſes and ſyng in a fewe Dirige grotes, then beſtowe an houre in readyng the Bible to their paryſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Again, Nabuchodonozor a pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of high dignitie honour and worſhyp, whom all people, kynredes &amp; tongues wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully feared, was for his proud ſtomacke &amp; ſtiffe heart againſt god and his word cleane depoſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſo plagued, that he fel from that mooſt renowmed dignitie and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of a kyng to the felowſhyp of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes: he refuſed the companye of men and became beaſtly hearted enclining hymſelf altogyther to company with Aſſes: and in ſteade of his ſumptuous and pryncely diſhes, was very glad to feede moſt gredily like an Oxe on fair grene graſſe. Daniel .v. Furthermore whan God ſawe that the people folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the filthineſſe of their owne ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginacion, truſted in this and that, and claue not faſt vnto him but walked al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togyther in myſerable blyndnes, and appeared wonderous wilfull: for the rulers were cruell, the Iudges were wolfes, and the preiſtes wer light per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones,
<pb facs="tcp:3237:31"/> dyd muche iniurie and vtterly refuſed the ordinance of God, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not how lyttell the lawe was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of: with this the Lord greuouſely offended, ſpake vnto them mooſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently. Woe vnto you abhominable fylthye and cruell whyche wyll not heare nor be reformed, Sophonie the third Chapiter. Dauid the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete alſo, whiche coulde full well iudge the ſtrength of Goddes woord, for he made it alwaies his refuge and vſed it as his truſtie anker (ſaith vnto the Lorde) wherewithall ſhal youthe clenſe his waie? euen by rulyng hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after thy woord. This Prophet ſpake often full fayre vſyng moſt ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt woordes as a meane to atteigne his requeſte and peticion, wherein he deſired onely this, the Lord to teache hym his ſtatutes, declaryng that he would ſet all his delight and councell in them: yea, and continually talke of his wondres, makyng anſwere vnto all blaſphemers, my truſte is in thy word lorde. This holy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; works no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is able to improue, ſaid alſo vnto god. I haue more vnder ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng then all my teachers, for thy teſtimonies are my ſtudie. Pſal. Cxix.
<pb facs="tcp:3237:32"/> theſe places be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to encourage all men to read the Byble Who wold not hearyng this apply his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng in highe thynges? Who woulde not leaue his vanities and ſelfe ſtudie and giue ſygnes of a newe lyfe? who would not lamente to ſee what igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes guide the flocke of Chryſt? who would hearyng this, appeare a ſcoler to tradicions and a perſecutour of the word? who woulde not hearyng this, ſubmit his idle and ſuperſticiouſe hed to the obeyſaunce of the Byble? Who would hearyng this, folowe his own blynd ſeemyng and opinion? Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras ſaith, he that knoweth not that he ought to know, is but a brute beaſt amongeſt men. Who woulde not then with this Godly ſaiyng be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Byble? they that marke well ſentences of grauitie and worthy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, wyl not put reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder foote, and bee ſoo madde as to ſtretche their hand againſt the promoting of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. It is a token of a peſtilente and wycked heart to murmure at ſuche as reade it: For the time of them is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe that gloriouſly ſpend it, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that lyue ignoraunte as brute beaſtes. It ſemeth that ſuche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme
<pb facs="tcp:3237:32"/> the hight and ſupreme wiſedom of god to be vanities, ſurely we ought to celebrat thoſe daies with high ioye whan we once here tell that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſort geue ouer their enuious tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uails againſt the Byble. For then thei ſhall be greatly deſired, beloued and well named emongeſt al men, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ſedicion and diſcorde take their leaue and enter no more in place. Pitie it is that their yl intentes ſhuld condemne the Godly thinges that haue ben wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to winne them: they ought to yeld and giue greate thankes to God, that thei are deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Romiſhe aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. If they wold now ſhake of their old and duſty tradicions, &amp; abate their depraued malice, they mighte reſtore again their glorious fame and haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimacion, loue and fauour in ſteade of infamie, ſhame and diſdain. Surely it were a thyng moſt pleaſaunt in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſyght, to ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the rude mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude floriſh in his word, for in ſome places yet as great is the neclige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the people as the ignorance of preiſtes And that they thus continewe, weake wittes be not the cauſe, but very ſlou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and malice, whiche cauſe them to folowe the corrupcion of auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb facs="tcp:3237:33"/> and to ſet their heartes altogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on pleaſure &amp; idlenes. Thei thus folowyng their owne wilful intentes pulle doune ſtyll the eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. And yf they would leaue the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the worlde that nowe flocke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither ſtyffely in blyndneſſe, appliyng their wittes to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>domage other &amp; with their reſtye lyues cauſe ſedicion and ſclaunder vnto good miniſters: then myght Englande auaunce it ſelfe and ſaie. Now ſhal I floriſhe and haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure in goddes ſyght. Nowe ſhall I be valiaunt in vertues &amp; worthy great fame. For now there be none to troble and vex the poore ſort peceable people bent to the goſpell. Nowe ſhal ſcience augmente and men wyll drawe to the byble. Truely I could neuer hete An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique hiſtorie alledged that men ſhuld not knowe it. Now I ſhal weaken the hertes of mine enemies and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtande in dreade, they wyll feare me more for my knowledge, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for al my valeaunt conqueſtes. Now the heard hearted that were in credite and ſpred abroade the traines of ſuperſticiouſe doctrine, and with blynd flattery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giled the ſymple ſorte, wyl do ſeruice for my common weale. They wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb facs="tcp:3237:33"/> that men are but beaſtly by nature, and Godly by their cunnyng &amp; knowledge. And yet to ſaie further I haue often deſired to haue vyces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained and vertues augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; that it wil now come to paſſe I haue a full truſt, for my drad ſoueraigne lord and ſupreme head Kyng Edward the ſixt beginneth to be ſtable in the Lord and couragiouſe in his woord, and all his people within this his noble realme lyke louing ſubiectes be obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his grace &amp; perfectly taughte theyr duetie and obeiſaunce. Often Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath been in perill and daungier, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people were weake faint and dull of vnderſtandyng, by whoſe meane it ſomtime hath loſte the ſupreme heade and gouernour to it great ſorowe and care. But the pytiefull loſſe of noble Kyng Ihon ſhoulde perſe euery man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes heart moſt ſore, and by what trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous traines through falſe pretence he was caſte awaie, it is neceſſarye to be knowen, whoſe noble and valiaunt vertues worthely to extoll, I ſuppoſe no tongue is able. That noble Kyng was ſoo broughte vppe in vertuouſe and Godly bokes, and toke ſuch great trauell in the ſcriptures, that thereby
<pb facs="tcp:3237:34"/> he eſpyed how the glorie of God was ſhamefully duſked and defaced with wicked tradicions, ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry thinges moſt intollerable. Then he quickely like a prince of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and noble hearte, ſpake openlye he wold redreſſe the pompe and glorie of the cleargie, the goſpell ſhuld haue free paſſage let them al ſaie what thei luſt The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they like a multitude of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters turned themſelfes from naturall ſubiectes into beaſtly rebelles. They were ſoone confederate togyther lyke vile and deteſtable wretches to blud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die theyr handes on Goddes holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted their deere ſoueraigne Lorde and gouernour, &amp; al to mainteine Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſh auctoritie. And to their dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble intentes there wanted no trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe traynes, for whan they coulde not deuiſe howe to kyll hym neyther with ſword nor dagger, they inuented policie. Their daily ragyng and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe heartes were neuer at quietnes tyll they had encouraged with theyr peſtilent perſwaſions a ſturdy blacke Monke to take ſaie vnto his grace of a poyſoned cuppe, when his highneſſe valiauntly came into a certain Abbey where he ſtode in doubte and ſuſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:3237:34"/> of no man, for al the brethren recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued him, &amp; lyke Ipocrites fayned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes mery &amp; ioyeouſe outward, but were ſorowefull within. They vſed ioyeful wordes but bare wicked hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Thei ſorowed not for repentance, but at the ſight of his graces preſence whiche greued their heartes full ſore, then the Pryour archetectour of this heinouſe treaſon and father of al miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe eſpiyng oportunite of tyme brou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght in the Monke with his poyſoned cuppe. Oh Lord I maruel that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trels dyd not breake to offre ſo fylthy a draughte to ſo noble a King. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayl how his maliciouſe hand for ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour &amp; ſorow could hold the cup from fallyng. Wonder it was that feare of god, ſpeach of people and ſhame of the world dyd not reſtrayn his propenſed and wycked heart from that terryble draught deeathly vnto the Kyng and dampnable vnto hymſelfe. A wicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deede and a more myſerable myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe hathe not been heard of.</p>
            <p>O maliciouſe and vnhappy Monkes. O wretches I dare ſaie hearder hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then Pharaoo and falſer then Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, or els the inteſtyne of theyr hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes woulde haue trembled and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:3237:35"/> to betray theyr deere ſouerain lord. O wicked ſubiectes and beaſtes vnnatural, I ſaie again. O cruel wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tches, that ſoughte to make awaie hym for whoſe ſake they ſhould haue ſpent the beſt blud of their heartes, yf theſe ſhamefull villaynes had red the notable hiſtories of the Byble, they would haue reſtreigned their cankerd ſtomackes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſent to murder their kyng. If they had read the hiſtorye of kyng Dauid and Saul, and noted wel what reuerence &amp; loyall obeyſaunce Dauid ſhewed vnto Saull, although he knewe that he was a kyng vtterly caſt of and refuſed of god. If thei had marked alſo the wonderfull woordes and high diſpleſure that king Dauid toke with his ſeruaunte, whiche came vnto him (either lokyng for herty tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes orels ſome great reward) and ſaid he had killed Saull. The gentle heart of Dauid aroſe ſo at his woordes, and grudged ſo ſore at that heinouſe dede, that ſtraight he promoted his ſeruant euen to as good a death as the gibet or galowes. I thinke they woulde then haue ſtopped their wicked &amp; moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent purpoſe. O Lord, and yf they had knowen or at the leaſt wold haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen
<pb facs="tcp:3237:35"/> what reuerence ſubiectes oughte to ſhew to their hedes, thei wold haue tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled and quaked to haue conſpyred or thought any euel againſt their dere ſouerain lord. But theſe holy fathers euer as full of fables as falſe religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Quickely inuented howe they myght craftely cloke their wycked doynges and to ſtop the murmuring of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they reyſed this rumour that the kyng ſaied if he liued one twelmonth an half peny loofe ſhould be worth .xl. d. amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt them. Who doth not ſmell this to be a ſhamfull and a deteſtable lie? for his grace was tendre ouer the poore and louing to his ſubiectes, and neuer pretended nether to them ne yet to the publikewelth any ſuch domage He was in dede earneſtly bent and ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry couragious to ſet forth the wil and pleaſure of God, and for this cauſe onely they wrought his confuſion. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las theſe fathers were men ſworne to obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet thei neither preached the trace of it, ne yet folowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, they ſhould haue been full of good graces, but thei emploied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes to wicked vorage &amp; tirannie, thei ſtudied ſo ſoore to augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their liuelod, that thei had neuer leaſure to thincke on the hyghe
<pb facs="tcp:3237:36"/> and ſupreme wiſdome of god. Wherof whoſoeuer hath taſtedfully wil neuer grudge againſt his king or Prince, for the knowlege of it adiuigneth the her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of al ſubiects moſt ſtraightly vnto their dere ſouerain lord, the ſtrength &amp; vertue of it is ſuche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wil neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre any ſparke of treaſon to dwell in a ſubiectes hert. It pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth ſuch loue &amp; faithful obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce where it goeth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corrupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can find no place to enter. Treaſon is a thyng ſo horible vnto it, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not endure to thinke on the plagues that it iuſtly deſerueth Yea, it is of this nature, that al ſynne &amp; wickednes is noiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vnto it, but of al other treaſon is the noyſomeſt, for it cauſeth riotouſe wittes repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to reaſon &amp; publique quietneſſe, to ſteere vp co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocions, to ſlaie innocentes, &amp; to folow wicked diſobedience, thynges moſt deteſted in Goddes ſyght. And if we prudently weigh what daunger it hathe often broughte vnto this noble realme, &amp; how it hath periſhed the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of honorable houſes, yea, &amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially howe it hath blotted the eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diſherited their ſonnes, ſhamed their progenie, &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the ſprites of al other their fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.
<pb facs="tcp:3237:36"/> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wil not ſuffre no ſuch fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to enter into our heades but gladly endeuor our ſelfes to read the Byble, for this is the waie to purge and cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe al treaſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery mannes heart. O Lord what obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it hath taught a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs within theſe fewe yeares, Who doth not knowe nowe what po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer God hath giuen a Kyng ouer his people? Who is ignorant what obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance is to be ſhewed to Goddes holy anointed? who ſo had marked the cum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming of our dere ſoueraine Lord king Edward the .vi. from the Towre vnto Weſtmi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter ſhuld haue ſeen and hard ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful tokens of true and louing her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. for al the noble citieze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey which came farre of on euery ſyde were there wonderfull ioyouſe to ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> daie, yea, to ſe the hope glory &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of al true Engliſh hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. The citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtudied forſoth very ſore howe to receaue his maieſtie moſt triumphantly as people willing to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare tokens of their obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heartes. Thei made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe, very gorgeouſe &amp; ſtode in humble order to receaue their deere lord &amp; ſupreme head, his toward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in vertues much ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt them made them wonderful ioyeouſe
<pb facs="tcp:3237:37"/> his highnes alſo appering perſonally before them al, a child of cumly, ſobre, and modeſt countenaunce, ſwete viſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and of face moſt beautiful, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo there wanted neyther godly edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion nor yet any acquired vertues, but in all thynges moſt perfectly fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſtreighte ſo allured &amp; drewe vnto him al their hertes that it was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der to ſe the ioie thei made, to behold their gouernour the peace and tranquillitie of the wealth of England ſo triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly paſſe through amongeſt them, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che again with gentle &amp; valiant coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance looked on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng rounde about hym on eueryſide, whoſe preſence euery man ſoo deſyred ſtanding in goodly order, that their ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es daſeled with long lokynge for that moſt gloriouſe ſyght, their heartes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo aked to bee deferred from it whiche paſſed ſo pleaſantly by. Then thei ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng ſtyll, prayed that his highneſſe might ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al other in vertue and nobilitie, and that god wold geue him grace eſpecially to walke in the waye of good deedes and in vertuouſe actes as he had entered, ſo to perſeuere, and that God would geue him an heart to loue vs his poore and faythfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes
<pb facs="tcp:3237:37"/> and worke for the common weale: yea, and that he may bee no acceptour of perſons but to regard the poore as well as the ryche. This Godly petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and other thynges there ſhewed were euident tokens of their faythful heartes, whiche are very muche to bee regarded for the loue of ſubiectes is the ſafiete of the kyng and the defence of the realme: Yea, he that hathe the loue of his ſubiectes hathe a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full treaſure. For I remember that I haue read an hiſtorie of Antique felici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of the world paſt worthy to bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. There was a certain ryght hygh and mightie prince, a man of excellent and profound vnderſtandyng, whoſe felicite was ſet altogither to haue the loue of his ſubiectes, deſiryng rather their weale then his owne priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie. It chaunced that certayne Prynces watred againſt him, he then made neither acte nor ſtatute, but ſent his louing letters amongeſt his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, deſiryng theym to healpe hym with money, then they conſyderyng full well his noble and tendre hearte towardes theym, and weere a people taughte but onely by nature to obeye their gouernoure, for they knewe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng
<pb facs="tcp:3237:38"/> of the lawe of GOD, ſpedily broughte into the treaſure houſe ſoo muche money as ſerued the kyng .vii. yeares, and yet whan the warres cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed there remained great plentie. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth theſe mennes gyftes were of gret pryce, but their good wylles were of greater. O gloriouſe tyme. O realme moſte happye where the kyng and his people were ſo knytte togither. And contrarilye there was one Tyberius the ſonne of Auguſt a deſtroyer of the people and very ſpytefull toward the Romaynes, lyghte of his dooeynges vſynge outragyouſe woordes vnto all good menne, yea, and of ſuche foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe preſumpcion and boldeneſſe in his realme that he thoughte he might dooe what he luſte in folowynge hys owne wycked and naughtie ententes. ¶ This Emperour was alſo prowde and furiouſe, which thyng fylled his ſubiectes heartes full of ſorowe and broughte vnto him ſelfe muche eyuell wyll and lyghte eſtymacion. And that well appeared. For after his deathe all the aunciente fathers and nobles of Rome with the reſte of the people made greate Sacryfice and earneſte peticion. Vnto the GODDES to
<pb facs="tcp:3237:38"/> ſende Tyberes ſolle into the furies of Hell, he had wrought theim ſo muche ſorowe, that they would hym no ioye nor yet any part of the Goddes glory. ¶ O the infelicite and daungerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Rome in thoſe daies when the Kyng and his people murmured one at another. For no man that hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wyll repugne vnto this, but that realm is wel warded, where the kyng and his ſubiectes bee of mutuall loue and fidelitie. Nowe therfore vtterly to auoyde all contencion and dyſcorde and to plante for euer amongeſt vs a ſtable and louely ſocietie of lyuyng, there is no better meane then to arme oure ſelfes with vnitie and concorde drawyng al in one line to promote the Goſpell of Chryſt, and to enlarge our heartes to receaue Godly and gentle perſwaſions as menne very wyllyng to preſente theym ſelfes to the Byble, and to flee vnto it as vnto our mooſte truſtie porte, and gladly receaue that heauenly treaſure. If wee thus dooe all ſtrangers ſhal feare vs as they did the ſonnes of Iacob, and (accordyng vnto the holy Prophete) our purpoſe ſhall proſpere and come well to paſſe: yea, and ſuche ſhewe wyll appeare of
<pb facs="tcp:3237:39"/> vs that men wyl not ſuffre our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to peryſhe, but to renoume vs as people of vertue and worthy commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion. Wherfore mooſt humbly wee oughte nowe to praie the lord, that he would put awaie all lettes from their ſtomackes that grudge ſecretly at his holy woord, and make light of the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that heauenly treaſure ſet to ſhew amongeſt vs in euery churche. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto yf we beare faint and ſturdy her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, let vs bee well aſſured, the Lorde wyl blaſte and blot our doynges with euell fortune and enuiouſe miſhap, for as farre as I haue read, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Emperour, Kyng nor yet Prynce that proſpered, whiche tooke parte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, thou maieſt fynde in diuerſe notable places of the Bible how God ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> punyſhed with greuouſe plagues and durable ſtrookes many regyons whiche reiected and made light of his word. Again there is nothyng neither in heauen aboue nor in yearth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo pleaſaunte and acceptable in God the fathers ſyght, as to haue his liuely woorde that heauenly treaſure moſt thankefully receaued and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red amongeſt vs. O then thou counter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fayted Chriſtian, what ſpirite of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:3237:39"/> moueth the to murmure at ſuche as read thenglyſhe Bible? Wonder it is that thou art not aſhamed to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt thy ſelfe any of Chriſtes felowſhippe, for in contempnyng and making light of his goſpell thou declareſt thy ſelfe a right Paganime or rather a Iewe, yea, I ſaie thy longe prayer often fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng and almoſe deedes and all good woorkes that thou canſt deuiſe, ſhall nothyng preuayle the: But appeare plainely in Goddes ſight as thynges moſt vile &amp; deteſtable, ſo longe as thou beareſt a ſuperſticiouſe hearte towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des his bleſſed Teſtament. Alas ſuffre not thy ſelf no longer to be begiled, ſet before thy face what doctrine Moiſes taught the people in the .vi. of Deutro He ſtraightely charged them to keepe the lawe of God in their heartes, and willed them alſo to teach it vnto their chyldren and talke of it vnto their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, this place ſhuld wake the out of thy dootyng dreames. Sterevppe thy heart for ſhame vnto Chryſtes goſpell and reuerence it wherſoeuer thou goeſt, wherevnto bee al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and prayſe. Amen</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:40"/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the pariſhe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes Church within new gate by Richard Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Prynter to our ſoueraigne lorde Kyng Edward the <hi>.VI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1547.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3237:40"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
